Waco Art League records, Inclusive: 1900-1989, undated, Bulk: 1958-1989
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Waco Art League records
Inclusive: 1900-1989, undated, Bulk: 1958-1989
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
784
Waco Art League
7 folders 1 OVZ document box
The Waco Art League records document women's interest in the arts in Waco. The records include minutes, by-laws, yearbooks, programs, newspaper clippings, and a scrapbook.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The Waco Art League was organized by Charles H. Cox in Waco in 1900. Cox, an Englishman who was active in the Waco cotton business, and an accomplished watercolor artist, was the first president, and only male member of the club. The club was formed by a number of Waco women to encourage and stimulate art appreciation in local schools and the community. The league met monthly and hosted talks given by artists from various backgrounds and disciplines. They also sponsored art shows and exhibits.
The group was involved with civic projects such as bringing art into local schools and hosting art competitions as part of the Waco Cotton Palace. With the desire to open an art museum, the league members collected and displayed artwork in locations throughout Waco such as the public library and YWCA. A museum fund was set aside, but as years passed, this idea was not realized. Eventually the fund and profits of art sales went to other local organizations. In addition, the group provided financial assistance locally in the form of Baylor University student art scholarships and donations to institutions such as the YWCA of Waco, Waco Art Center, and the Armstrong Browning Library at Baylor University.
The organization celebrated their 90th Anniversary in 1990, but as of 2021 it is no longer in operation.
Scope and Content
The Waco Art League records represent the artistic interests of women in Waco, Texas. The Administrative series includes a history, minutes, ledgers, correspondence, and a scrapbook. The scrapbook is the most comprehensive piece in the collection as it spans from 1900 to 1985; however, the bulk of the book is representative of events that took place in the 1960s and 1970s. The Publications series includes early event programs and organizational yearbooks.
Arrangement
The records had no previous discernible arrangement. Currently, the collection is arranged in two series: I. Administrative and Series II. Publications.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 784. Acquired 1974-07-29
Related Resources
Related references
“Waco Art League 90th Birthday.” The Waco Citizen (Waco, TX). 1990 November 16.
Index Terms
Subjects
Art -- Texas -- Waco.; Women -- Texas -- Waco -- Societies and clubs.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Minutes (Records); Programs (Publications).; Scrapbooks.; Yearbooks.
- Administrative, 1900-1989, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The ledger consists of notes from around the 1930s. The scrapbook provides the most information about the group and includes items from 1900-1985, mostly concentrated in the 1960s to 1970s. By-laws, limited correspondence, newspapers clippings, photographs, yearbooks, programs, and a list of past presidents are present. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - History, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ledger, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1900-1985 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, circa 1958-circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1969-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Publications, 1929-1968; 2
  The Publications series is dated 1929-1968. The series includes programs and yearbooks which denote activities and membership of the organization. Yearbooks, mostly from the 1960s and 1970s, can also be found in the Scrapbook held in the Administrative series. The series is arranged chronologically and in good condition.
  - Programs, 1929-1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Yearbooks, 1938, 1949, 1955-1961, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)